<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xwayland_surface_association_v1">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2022 Joshua Ashton

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="Protocol for associating X11 windows to wl_surfaces">
    This protocol allows an Xwayland server to associate an X11 Window to a wl_surface.

    Before this protocol, this would be done via the Xwayland server providing the
    wl_surface's resource id via the WL_SURFACE_ID atom on the X window.
    This was problematic as a race could occur if the wl_surface associated with a WL_SURFACE_ID
    for a window was destroyed before the update of the atom was processed by the compositor and
    another surface (or other object) had taken it's id due to recycling.

    This protocol solves that by moving the X11 Window to wl_surface association step to the
    Wayland side, which means that the association cannot happen out-of-sync with the resource
    lifetime of the wl_surface.
  </description>

  <interface name="wp_xwayland_surface_association_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="context object for surface association manager">
      The Xwayland surface association manager is a singleton global object that
      provides the ability to create a wp_xwayland_surface_association_v1 object
      for a given wl_surface.

      This interface is intended to be bound by the Xwayland server.

      If this interface is bound by an Xwayland server, it must: not
      set the WL_SURFACE_ID atom on any X11 window.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the surface association manager"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_surface_association">
      <description summary="get a surface association object">
        Create a surface association interface for a given wl_surface object.
      </description>

      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="wp_xwayland_surface_association_v1"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="wp_xwayland_surface_association_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="interface for associating Xwayland windows to wl_surfaces">
      A interface used for associating Xwayland windows to wl_surfaces.
    </description>

    <request name="associate">
      <description summary="associates a Xwayland window to a wl_surface">
        Associates an Xwayland window to a wl_surface.

        The X server associated with the XID `window` is determined by the
        wl_client making the request.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="window" type="uint" summary="Window XID"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the surface association object">
        Destroy the surface association manager.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
